All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is למד טית.
Lamed Tet. We pick up with למד חית עמוד בית. Lamed Chet
Amud Bet. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, which is about ten lines from
the bottom, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10 lines.
Line starts with the word כרבי עקיבא דמתניתין. K'Rebbi Akiva d'Matnisin. So
the גמרא, Gemara, the end of yesterday's דף Daf has just worked
out figuring out what everybody does with the various פסוקים Psukim of
אשר לא ארשה. Asher lo orasa. But just to remind you, bottom
line is we have three opinions. Right? The תורה Torah says נערה
בתולה אשר לא ארשה ושכב עמה, Naara Besula Asher Lo Orasa Veshachav
Ima, who has who has not been betrothed. So what if
she has been betrothed, but is not currently? If she has and
is currently, then everybody agrees there's no payment because then it's קים
ליה בדרבא מיניה. Kim Lei Bidraba Minei. She's a married woman and
it's חייב מיתה. Chayav Misa. But if she has been betrothed and
it's only it's only אירוסין Erusin not נישואין, Nissuin, so she can
still be a בתולה, Besula, and now she's divorced. So there it's
a debate.
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose HaGlili says, okay, so it doesn't satisfy
the criteria the same way as she's not a נערה, Naara, the
same way as she's not a בתולה, Besula, no קנס. Knas. רבי
עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, there are two versions of רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva.
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva in our משנה Mishna says she gains independence
from her father and therefore the קנס Knas she gets, a קנס
Knas but it goes to her. It should be noted that normally
a woman who is who is מאורסה Me'orasa and then divorced, not
נישואין Nissuin but מאורסה Me'orasa and then divorced, is not independent of
her father. A woman should become a woman, a young girl could
become independent of her father after נישואין Nissuin and then divorce, but
after אירוסין Erusin and then divorce, not. But in this case רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says the תורה Torah is telling you that she
has enough independence so she gets a קנס Knas and it goes
to her, not to her father. And the רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
of the ברייתא Baraita says that no, that actually the פסוק Pasuk
really means nothing. I mean, it doesn't come to exclude anything and
therefore in this case it would be a standard case. If she
had אירוסין Erusin and divorce, it would go to her father. So
three possibilities: nobody gets it after אירוסין Erusin and divorce; father gets
it, so no change in the law; or רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
of the משנה Mishna she gets it. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
picks up. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, ten lines from the bottom on
למד חית עמוד בית. Lamed Chet Amud Bet. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
our rabbis taught.
קנסה למי? Knaso l'mi? לאביה. L'aviha. Who gets the קנס? Knas? The
father. ויש אומרים לעצמה. Ve'yesh omrim le'atzmah. Some say she gets it.
So this ברייתא Baraita is in no particular context that it's talking
about the case of אירוסין. Erusin. It sounds like it's just talking
about a regular case. So the גמרא Gemara says לעצמה? Le'atzmah? She
keeps it? אמאי? Amai? Why should she keep the קנס? Knas? It
sounds like it's giving a regular ruling. So אמר רב נחמן, Amar
Rav Nachman, הכא במאי עסקינן... Hacha b'mai askinan... I'm sorry,
אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, הכא בנערה שנתארסה ונתגרשה עסקינן. Hacha
b'naara shenisorasa venisgarsha askinan. We're talking about the case of our משנה.
Mishna. There was אירוסין Erusin and then divorce.
כמפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי עקיבא דמתניתין ורבי עקיבא דברייתא. K'mifligi biflugta d'Rebbi Akiva
d'Matnisin v'Rebbi Akiva d'Baraita. And this is the debate of רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva of the משנה Mishna that says that in that case
it goes to herself, she becomes emancipated partially, and רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva of the ברייתא Baraita that says the law does not change
if there is אירוסין Erusin and divorce. Okay, so that's a nice
summary of the two positions of רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, says Abaye. בא עליה ומתה פטור. Ba aleha u'mesa patur.
If he had sex with her and she died, not in the
act of sex, it could be, but afterwards, okay. So he raped
her and then she's dead at the time when the payment is
supposed to take place. The person is exempt, even though the payment
goes to the father. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, because the verse says ונתן לאבי
הנערה. Venasan l'avi ha'naara. At the time of the payment he has
to be the father of the נערה, Naara, which seems like we're
able to point to her and say there she is. ולא לאבי
מתה. Velo l'avi mesa. And not that she is dead at that
time. Now this could be understood as a גזירת הכתוב, Gezeiras hakasuv,
but one of the things that we're going to see about, you
know, within the issue about paying the father is the question about
is the payment understood to go directly to the father or is
the payment conceptually to
her, but it is then you know somehow it's paid to her
and then it transfers from her to the father? Okay, but fundamentally
the obligation is to her, but then it goes through her and
then because the father basically collects for her because he's entitled to
her earnings at this age, she's a קטנה Ktana or a נערה
Naara or whatever, he's entitled to any money that comes as a
result of her. But fundamentally it's the obligation to her, but once
it's paid to her then it transfers, like paying an עבד Eved
and it goes to the עבד Eved it goes to the master.
So it's paid to her and then it goes to the father.
So one thing that supports that understanding of it is this הלכה
Halacha that if she is dead at the time of payment, nobody
gets it. If it was fundamentally an obligation to the father, then
this would just be a גזירת הכתוב, Gezeiras hakasuv, which maybe it
is. But if fundamentally it's an obligation to her and she's not
around to be paid, then nobody gets it. That's what אביי Abaye
says. Yes? Are these קנסות Knasot also adjudicated through the formal process
of בית דין? Beis Din? Yes. Okay, so there's a whole long
process. Once the בית דין Beis Din makes a ruling and then
you know... well, right. Then once once בית דין, Beis Din, there's
a so that's a whole different discussion that we're going to get
to that all in the next פרק, Perek, which is if בית
דין פוסק, Beis Din paskens, not when actually the guy takes out
his wallet. If בית דין פסק Beis Din pasak while she was
alive and adjudicated the case and said okay now you're חייב Chayav
to the father, then... And she was alive at that space time
and said, okay, now you're חייב chayiv to the father fifty כסף,
kesef, and then she died, the debt now, once בית דין Beis
Din adjudicated, now there's a straight debt to the father. So that's
a good point. After the adjudication, it's not that physically the money
is paid to her and transferred, it's that the obligation is to
her, but once בית דין Beis Din rules on it, then it
has crystallized as then his obligation to the father. So this would
be a case where she died before the case was adjudicated, before
בית דין Beis Din came out with their ruling. And then, since
she's not around, there's nobody that can essentially bring him to court,
there's nobody that he actually is obligated to. But once בית דין
Beis Din rules, then בית דין Beis Din makes him pay the
father, and that becomes the nature of the obligation. Yes. Isn't there
the possibility that conceptually the money is given her but goes to
the father to hold and to use? Well, I'm not saying to
hold and use. The father can go ahead and take it and
put it in his own bank account, but because it's like a
principle about מה שקנה עבד קנה רבו, ma shakana eved kana rabo,
you know, or שבח נעורים לאביה, shvach neurim l'aviha, so the father
doesn't have to hold it on her behalf. Any money that comes
as a result of her, he's entitled to. Okay? So this money
came as a result of her, he's entitled to it, but fundamentally
it's money that was hers, it's just he's entitled to it. So
my question was, is it, is it possible that the idea that
fundamentally hers reflected by the use of the word לעצמה le'atzma as
opposed to simply לה? lah? When it says קנסה לעצמה? knasah le'atzma?
Yeah. I don't know, but that's a case when it maybe, maybe.
I mean, that might just be under, just done to emphasize, you
know, לאביה l'aviha or עצמה. atzma. It's a stronger, it's just a
clearer contrast. But I don't know, because anyway, that's a case where
it really is hers. Into the, the conception, the question here is
when it's the father's, how is the father getting it? Okay, so
אביי Abaye says that if she's dead, and Michael correctly points out,
meaning dead not at the time he takes out his wallet, but
dead at the time that they go to בית דין, Beis Din,
then there is no obligation. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מילתא
דפשיטא ליה לאביי, milsa d'pshita lei l'Abaye, is the thing that אביי
Abaye took for granted, that if she's dead there's no payment. איבעיא
ליה לרבא. ibaya lei l'Rava. רבא Rava didn't know. רבא Rava had
a question about that. דאיבעיא רבא. d'ibaya Rava. Now we're going to
see רבא Rava actually had a different question, but based on רבא's
Rava's different question we're going to try to uncover what his assumption
is about this case of אביי. Abaye. דאיבעיא רבא. d'ibaya Rava. רבא
Rava asked, יש בגר בקבר או אין בגר בקבר? yesh bagar bakever
o ein bagar bakever? Is there, does does maturity happen in the
grave or not? Meaning, if the girl dies as a נערה, na'arah,
and then by the time it's time for בית דין, Beis Din,
had she been alive, she would have been a בוגרת. bogeret. Does
the law change now based on what her status would have been
when it finally gets to court had she still been alive? Okay.
It is a legal system that recognizes that. It is totally bizarre.
So let's take a look at, let's spell out what the implications
are. So I remember there was this joke, it was so funny,
but anyway, this guy's filling out an application form and it says,
"Age of parents if alive," so he writes like 140. So the
guy says, "140? How is that?" Says, "So if they were alive,
they'd be 140!"
Alright, anyway, so alright, so anyway, יש בגר בקבר. yesh bagar bakever.
So the גמרא Gemara says דאיבעיא רבא יש בגר בקבר או אין
בגר בקבר. d'ibaya Rava yesh bagar bakever o ein bagar bakever. יש
בגר בקבר? yesh bagar bakever?
Is there, does maturation occur in the grave, ודבנה הוי, u'dibnah havei,
and therefore her son will inherit?
So basically we're assuming that this woman already has a child. Okay.
The גמרא's Gemara's going to ask how's that possible if she's so
young, but let's bracket that for a minute. This woman has a
child, and therefore what happens if, let's assume she's alive. Okay, the
guy raped her, she was a נערה, na'arah, it comes to court,
she's a בוגרת. bogeret. Yes? So now, if she's a בוגרת bogeret
at the time it comes to court, then everybody agrees a בוגרת
bogeret is emancipated from her father, and then everybody would agree the
payment goes to her. By the way, that's another good evidence that
fundamentally it's her payment, because if she's a בוגרת bogeret at the
time it comes to court, then you pay her, you don't pay
the father. Okay? Clear? Okay. So, let's say she was not a
בוגרת bogeret when it came to court because she was dead when
it came to court, but had she been alive, she would have
been a בוגרת. bogeret. Is the payment now to her? Now, she's
not alive, but if she has a child, it will then go
to the child. Or do we say since she is dead, therefore
the payment still is to the father, not to her, and the
father gets the payment? יש בגר בקבר דבנה הוי? yesh bagar bakever
dibnah havei? Is there, you know,
does maturation occur in the grave and therefore it's like it's now
the obligation is to her because now she's as if she were
alive a בוגרת bogeret and therefore passes on to her son, her
child? או דילמא אין בגר בקבר? o dilma ein bagar bakever? Or
no, we don't look at her as a בוגרת, bogeret, we look
at her as a נערה na'arah because she's not alive and she's
still a נערה, na'arah, ודאביה הוי, u'd'aviha havei, and therefore the father
still remains the one who is entitled to it. Okay, so that's
רבא's Rava's question. Now both of those basically assume, now the גמרא
Gemara isn't done yet, but let's just point out that both of
those assume that if the girl is dead at the time it
comes to court. payment will still be made, right? Both of those
assume against אביי. Abaye. The only question is to whom does the
payment go? Does it go to her, as it were, and therefore
to her child, or does it go to the father? But even
if she's dead at the time it comes to court, fundamentally there
still is the obligation to pay. Now the גמרא Gemara is going
to unpack רבא Rava before it gets back to the אביי. Abaye.
Okay, ומי מיבעיא? umi mibaya? ומי מיעברי? umi ma'abra?
How can you say she's pregnant? How can you have the scenario
that she died before she became a בוגרת bogeres and she has
a child? So that basically means that a woman as a נערה
na'arah can conceive and give birth before she becomes a בוגרת. bogeres.
Okay, well, maybe as a קטנה, ktana, maybe as a קטנה, ktana,
but okay, but still before she becomes a בוגרת. bogeres. ומי מיעברי?
umi ma'abra? ותני רב ביבי קמיה דרב נחמן, v'tani Rav Bibi komei
d'Rav Nachman, רב ביבי Rav Bibi taught before רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
שלש נשים, shlosha nashim,
you'll remember this, this is a nice thing we've had a few
times starting in יבמות, Yevamos, very important nowadays for issues around birth
control. שלש נשים משמשות במוך, shlosh nashim meshamshot bamoch,
three women can use a מוך, moch, this is the sponge that
prevents, absorbs the sperm and prevents the woman from getting pregnant. אלו
הן, eilu hen, and these are they, קטנה ומעוברת ומניקה, ktana u'meuberet
u'meinika,
a קטנה, ktana, an underage girl, a pregnant woman, and a nursing
woman. קטנה שמא תתעבר ותמות, ktana shema titaber vetamut, an underage girl
because we're afraid she'll get pregnant and she'll die as a result
of the pregnancy. מעוברת שמא תעשה עוברה סנדל, meuberet shema ta'aseh ubarah
sandal,
a pregnant woman because we're afraid that as a result of the
way רש"י Rashi explains it, we believe that a second child could
be conceived while she's pregnant with the first one and that will
crush the first child. תוספות Tosfos says that's not possible, תוספות Tosfos
says but nevertheless somehow the sperm will adversely affect the second the
first child. מניקה שמא תגמול את בנה, meinika shema tigmol es benah,
and a nursing woman because if she gets if she conceives and
has another child, then that pregnancy and maybe the second birth will
interfere with her nursing of the current child and therefore it'll compromise
the health of the first child. So therefore we don't want these
three women to get pregnant. Now I should pause and remind you
that there's an important debate of, first of all, there's the debate
of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos which is we already saw before
whether the מוך moch is something used before or after. Okay, this
is important because how problem... well, let me just sort of point
it out, and then I'll say and then the next debate is
when it says these three women use a מוך moch and others,
so the question is what does that mean? These three women must
use a מוך, moch, are obligated, and other women are allowed but
not obligated, or is it these three women are allowed to use
a מוך moch and other women are forbidden. Okay, so that if
you have an approach that other women are forbidden, then you're putting
on the table that there are some forms of possible birth control,
you know, that could be forbidden, presumably because they destroy the sperm.
And then the question is which forms are they? Is it the
act of wiping out the sperm afterwards? And that's forbidden because that's
like an active destroying of the sperm, you know, in a very
physical way, wiping out the sperm and destroying it. Or is it
the form of birth control... or is it the sponge was inserted
before? And the reason it's forbidden is because in the act of
ejaculation it's not totally entering into the woman's body, but it's sort
of spilling out of the woman's body, which would be the problem
of like a condom. Okay, so if you say that there's an
opinion here that it's forbidden under certain circumstances, then it's critically important
to understand what type, what's the מוך, moch, and to understand what
type of things might be problematic about this. So you can understand
that this גמרא Gemara is like the most central גמרא Gemara about
forms of birth control, contemporary forms of birth control. Anyway, so that's
the position. And then it says,
ואיזו היא קטנה, v'eizu hi ktana, what is considered a minor girl?
מבת אחת עשרה שנה ויום אחד, mibas achas esre shanah veyom echad,
eleven years and
a day. עד שתים עשרה שנה ויום אחד, ad shtem esre shanah
veyom echad, until twelve years and one day. פחות מכאן, pachot mikan,
less than eleven years isn't a problem because you don't think that
she'll conceive. ויתר על כן, veyeser al ken, and more than twelve
years isn't a problem because she'll conceive and she'll be... it won't
endanger her life. משמשות כדרכן והולכות. meshamshot kedarka v'oleches. It's actually like
actually harmful to her. אביי? Abaye?
All right, that the גמרא Gemara was not concerned about. These were
when they were getting married that young and they didn't think that
it would be, apparently they didn't think it would be that harmful.
Anyway, before and afterwards they don't have to worry about this birth
control, about this מוך. moch. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabi Meir, this
is what רבי מאיר Rabi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים אחת זו ואחת
זו משמשות כדרכן והולכות. v'chachamim omrim achas zu v'achas zu meshamshot kedarka
v'oleches. Even these women, the young girl and the pregnant woman, they
can go ahead and they either are not allowed to use this
birth control or don't have to worry about this birth control, even
though you pointed out certain dangers. No, מן השמים ירחמו, min hashamayim
yerachamu, they'll have compassion from heaven, people are allowed to take these
types of risks, okay, שנאמר, shene'emar, it says, שומר פתאים ה', shomer
psa'im Hashem, God watches over the foolish. So that's also fascinating like...
it's the opposite of the general principle, no? Of having to take
care of your own health. And not relying on a נס. nes.
Exactly. So the question is why are they saying this? So if
you say that it's a... that that the issue is that under
normal circumstances you might not be allowed to do it... then this
leads to an enormous amount of stringency associated with issues of like
זרע לבטלה zera l'vatalah because then they're even saying that you should
be taking risks to your life prior to using certain forms of
birth control. So you can understand how weighty that that adds to
the whole conversation. But if it's saying whether you're obligated or not,
then they're just saying like we are not going to halakhically mandate
people to, you know, take certain health precautions. Now part of the
reason might be because this is like דרך העולם derech ha'olam like
what the גמרא Gemara says in another
context, כיון דדש דש, kivan didash dash, which is once the ground
has been trampled on it's been trampled on, which means if people
do this as a regular type of a practice, we cannot legally
forbid it because of your need to, you know, take care of
your own health, okay, which is like for example רב משה פיינשטיין
Rav Moshe Feinstein basically said that when it came to smoking. We
should forbid smoking because it's obviously adversely, you know, it's terrible for
somebody's health, but something that's an accepted practice, you know, we're gonna
say like okay whatever, you know, it's bad for somebody else's health.
Well, that's also true. Anyway, so they might basically it's just saying
like, you know what, this doesn't happen all the time that danger
happens and we can't therefore mandate that you not do these types
of, that you, you know, do these types of things. Anyway, that's
a fascinating discussion which I don't want to get into, but that's
basically the debate. What's relevant for us is that it says that
a girl will die if she becomes pregnant under twelve years old,
so therefore we have to assume that if she got pregnant, she
got pregnant after she was twelve years old. Now of course you
could say it says that she might die. We could still be
talking about a scenario that she got pregnant under twelve. Now by
the way, she had to be a בתולה, besulah, so what's the
story in order to pay the קנס? knas? So the story is
he raped her let's say and then afterwards, afterwards she had sex
with somebody else or she got pregnant as a result of the
rape. Okay, and if he did it as a קנס, knas, let's
assume not like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that you pay the קנס
knas as a קטנה. ktana. So then she could have gotten pregnant
when she was raped as a קטנה ktana and had a child
before she became a בוגרת, bogeret, had a child at, you know,
before twelve and a half, before she became a בוגרת. bogeret. But
the גמרא Gemara is assuming, even though the language here is lest
she become pregnant and die, the גמרא Gemara is assuming that if
she becomes pregnant she'll definitely die, so we can only be talking
about a case where she became pregnant after twelve. And then there's
no time to give birth to a child before she became a
בוגרת, bogeret, because a בוגרת bogeret occurs six months after twelve years
old. So let's just read that, so the גמרא Gemara says: וכי
תימא דעברה כשהיא נערה, v'chi teima d'ibra k'shehi na'arah,
so we're assuming she can't become pregnant out of a קטנה ktana
without dying as a result, so therefore she can only become pregnant
as a נערה. na'arah. ואולידה כשהיא נערה v'olida k'shehi na'arah and then
still gave birth before she became a בוגרת bogeret because remember we
want her to have become a בוגרת bogeret in the grave for
our scenario, she died before she became a בוגרת, bogeret, okay? And
therefore she and we want to ask whether the child inherits. So
she had to have become pregnant as a נערה na'arah and given
birth as a נערה. na'arah. ובשיתא ירחי מי קיילדה, u'v'shita yarchei mi
ka-yalda,
since when can a woman give birth in six months? והאמר שמואל
v'ha'amar Shmuel and we know that she only has six months before
she's a בוגרת. bogeret. דאמר שמואל, d'amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says: אין
בין נערות לבגרות אלא ששה חדשים. ein bein na'arut l'bagrut ela shisha
chodashim.
There's only six months from the time of נערות na'arut till she
becomes a בוגרת. bogeret. וכי תימא בציר הוא דליכא, v'chi teima batzir
hu d'leika,
maybe שמואל Shmuel says there's not fewer than six months, less than
six months. הא טפי איכא, ha tfei ika, maybe it could be
longer, maybe it's not just a strict thing about six months on
the calendar but there needs to be physical
aspects of maturity, you know, and the body has to be and
the גמרא Gemara when it describes בגרות bagrut describes certain stages of
development of the body, so maybe under some cases it would be
longer than six months, enough time to have a child. So the
גמרא Gemara says: הא אלא קאמר, ha ela ka'amar,
שמואל Shmuel says there's only six months, which means it'll never be
more than six months. So the גמרא Gemara assumes and by the
way, it is worth pointing this out again, you know we always
say oh twelve years and two pubic hairs, that's a נערה. na'arah.
Six months later you're a בוגרת. bogeret. Actually in the גמרא, Gemara,
בוגרת bogeret is actually determined by physical states of maturity of the
body, but it's just that שמואל Shmuel says that will never be
take more than six months. It's sort of like, excuse the analogy,
but it's אמוראי amora'i in the פסח Pesach mode because it's three
weeks away from פסח, Pesach, it's sort of like we say oh
eighteen minutes, you know, is, you know, from the time you add
the water if you leave it out of the oven and you
don't work it then it becomes חמץ. chametz. The גמרא Gemara doesn't
say eighteen minutes. The גמרא Gemara says that you look at the
dough to see if it actually has fermented based on whether it's
cracking and there's a crust and there's whatever, what the dough looks
like. But in one place the גמרא Gemara indicates that that won't
happen in less than eighteen minutes. So therefore rather than having to
actually look at a physical assessment and case by case we just
say eighteen minutes. Okay, so the same thing happens here. The גמרא
Gemara determines בוגרת bogeret based on a physical maturation of the body
after the two pubic hairs, but שמואל Shmuel says it'll never take
more than six months, so we just say okay six months after.
I mean that's like how we tend to think of it. Okay,
but if what now that we're realizing six months after and assuming
she can't become pregnant as a
נערה na'arah as a
קטנה ktana without dying as
a
result. So you don't have the scenario of her becoming בוגרת בקבר
Bogeret bakever in the grave and wondering if the money should be
paid to the child. Okay, now you could still say, but let's
pay the money to the other heirs. But the problem is, who's
the next heir of this woman if she has no children? The
father. So then it's a moot question. Is there בגרות בקבר Bagrut
bakever and you pay it to her heirs, meaning the father, or
there's no בגרות בקבר Bagrut bakever and you pay it to the
father? So it's not an interesting question. Yes, Michael, you want to
say something about this? Because the גמרא Gemara took it for granted
that she could have given birth twice or there was someone else,
there's אין איש נוחל את אשתו... Ein ish nochel et ishto... I
guess so, once you buy into that hypothesis, yeah. All right, so
fine, yes. Is what you
just explained relevant also to the relationship between תם Tam and בטל
בשישים, Batil beshishim, in other words, you're never going to have תם...
Tam... Oh yeah, similar, I mean it's a general idea of always
trying to use a quantifiable number rather than assessment, yeah. Sure, yep,
absolutely. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, so that's the question. So we don't understand how you can
formulate your question, because practically you won't have the scenario. אלא הכי
קמיבעיא ליה, Ela hachi kamibaya lei, fine, this was רבה's Rava question.
יש בגר בקבר ופקע אב? Yesh bager bakever ufaka av? Do we
say she becomes a בוגרת Bogeret in the grave and the father
is, you know, sort of rejected, like sort of removed, thank you.
או דילמא אין בגר בקבר ולא פקע אב? O dilma ein bager
bakever velo paka av? Or there's no בגר בקבר Bager bakever and
the father is not removed. So if she becomes a בוגרת Bogeret
in the grave, we would say that, okay, so we look at
her as though she's a בוגרת Bogeret now in court. Right? It's
come to court, she's dead, but she's in the grave, but had
she been alive she would have been a בוגרת. Bogeret. So therefore
we say, well, as a בוגרת Bogeret this case would not involve
the father, it would only involve her. And she's not around. And
since she's not around, on the one hand we consider her a
בוגרת Bogeret even though she's dead, but since she's not around, but
once she's a בוגרת Bogeret the father is not relevant to this
court case. And since she's dead, she's not relevant to the court
case either, there's nobody to collect or whatnot, so then no payment
gets made. So if יש בגר בקבר Yesh bager bakever removes the
father from the equation and therefore there's no court case. If there's
אין בגר בקבר Ein bager bakever there's still your classic court case
and the father's in the equation and he's going to collect. But
both of these again assume against אביי, Abaye, that even though she
is dead, in theory there still could be a court case. Even
the position of יש בגר בקבר Yesh bager bakever is only because
she died and enough time passed that she would have been a
בוגרת. Bogeret. But if she just died and she still would have
been a קטנה Ktana or a נערה, Naarah, all of this assumes
that the money goes to the father. Okay? So all of this
assumes against אביי, Abaye, even if she's dead the money goes to
the father. The only question is had there been enough time that
she would have been a בוגרת, Bogeret, does that remove the father
from the equation? So now the גמרא, Gemara, that's one position that
rejects אביי. Abaye. Now we have another position of רבה Rava the
following way. מר בר רב אשי בעי לה הכי, Mar bar Rav
Ashi bei lah hachi, this is how מר בר רב אשי Mar
bar Rav Ashi raises the question.
מיתה עושה בגרות או אין עושה בגרות? Mita osa bagrut o ein
osa bagrut? Is death equivalent of בגרות? Bagrut?
Okay, meaning it's not about she becomes an adult in the grave,
but the same way when she becomes a בוגרת Bogeret she is
emancipated from her father, so you know, it's like למתים חפשי. Lametim
chofshi. So when she dies, she's also emancipated from the father. So
is the death itself something that kicks the father out of the
equation? Which that already basically is like אביי. Abaye. If בגרות Bagrut
kicks the father, death kicks the father out of the equation, it
means that once she died there's no longer going to be any
payment. Okay, that basically is like בגרות, Bagrut, it gets the father
out, she's dead, it gets the father out the same way when
she's a בוגרת, Bogeret, and since she's dead, nobody gets paid. Okay,
or no, death doesn't emancipate her, doesn't get the father out of
the equation, and the father will still be paid. Okay, so because
this is a קנס, Knas, right?
So part of it is because, yes, part of it Michael is
correct also, and that's what this תוספות Tosafot is, whether אין אדם
מוריש קנס לבניו Ein adam morish knas levanav is another question. Because
קנס Knas is very much as opposed to a debt which is
like a debt to an estate and doesn't need the person to
be alive, right? This is a קנס Knas and therefore it's very
much about the particular person that you have to pay to, not
just to an abstract debt that would go to that person's estate.
Okay, so this second version of it when the גמרא Gemara says
as רש"י Rashi says that the thing that was obvious to אביי
Abaye רבה Rava had a question about was this version of רבה.
Rava. The first version of רבה Rava rejects אביי, Abaye, assumes even
though she's dead there still will be a court case, the only
question is that if she would have been a בוגרת Bogeret had
she been alive does that get the father out? The second version
is asking אביי's Abaye question. Does her death get the father basically?
Exactly make it like she became a בוגרת, bogeres, get the father
out of the equation and since she's dead there's no court case,
so that's like אביי, Abaye, that if she's dead there's no court
case, or do we say it doesn't get the father out of
the even if she's dead there's still going to be a court
case and there's still can be money paid to the father. Yes?
Is fundamentally are we asking whether the קנס knas is a payment
to the injured or a penalty on the perpetrator? Well that is
in terms of this question, yes, I mean partly that's that and
partly it's also the question as I was saying about who is
the קנס knas to? Is it to her or to the father?
So you know there's two ways of looking at it. You're saying
even if I was to say the קנס knas is to her,
maybe you still pay after death because we still have to punish
the perpetrator. That's also correct, that's another element of it. So there's
two questions about it: who is it being paid to, her or
the father? And if she's dead and it's to her, presumably nobody
is going to collect, right? And also maybe he should—we should always
insist that he pays and who it eventually goes to is less
of our central concern because it's more about imposing the penalty on
him. That would be very similar to Yonit's idea. So this could
possibly apply to a case of נזק, nezek, right? Right, that's what
we said before. This is all very much about קנס knas because
otherwise שבת sheves hasn't been paid yet, צער, tzar, later the guy
dies, are you going to like actualize? Right, so תוספות Tosafos has
that whole discussion about the other payments, correct. So let's take a
look now as the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
תיקו, Teiku, alright we don't know the answer. So but those are
the questions. Now one last question, one last question before the next
משנה. Mishnah. בעי מיניה רבא מאביי. Baye minei Rava meiAbaye. רבא Rava
asked אביי. Abaye. בעל ונתארסה מהו? Ba'al ve'nisarsa mahu?
Let's say he had sex with her and she didn't die but
she became an ארוסה. arusah. And this is assuming like רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that had she—the one version, the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
of our משנה—that Mishnah had she been an ארוסה, arusah, had she
been נתארסה ונתגרשה nisarsa ve'nisgarsha at the time of the rape, then
she would get the payment. That that although normally אירוסין eirusin does
not emancipate the woman from the father's house, only נישואין nisuin does,
for this הלכה halakhah רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said it did. And
if she became an ארוסה וגרושה arusah u'grusha and then she was
raped, the payment would go to her. So let's say she was
raped before that happened and now she's an ארוסה. arusah. What would
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say in that situation? Right, would the payment
go to her now that they come to the court, right, when
the status has changed between the rape and when the case is
in the court? Similar to these other questions: she becomes a בוגרת
bogeres beforehand, she dies in the middle. So here let's say she
becomes an ארוסה arusah in the middle, will the money now go
to her? Would you say that it also go to the ארוס
arus just like הפרת נדרים? hafarat nedarim? There's a partnership between the
ארוס arus and then you know— No, no. The ארוס arus is
not זוכה zocheh to מעשה ידיה ma'aseh yadeha the same way the
father is. Okay, we always read בעל ועשה ba'al ve'asah a rape.
We're always going to— Yeah, I mean it could be מפתה, mefutah,
but in this case it's always about the rape. Okay, מהו? mahu?
So אמר ליה, amar lei, מי כתיב? mi ksiv? So אביי Abaye
said back to him, ונתן לאבי הנערה אשר לא ארשה? venasan la'avi
hana'arah asher lo orasah? It doesn't say pay the father of the
girl who is not betrothed. Meaning it doesn't say the issue of
not being betrothed at the moment of payment, it says that you
know when it says אשר לא ארשה asher lo orasah it was
about at the time of the act of rape. That's where it
mattered. At the time of the payment it doesn't matter whether or
not she's ארוסה arusah or not, it's still going to go to
the father. So he says back, ולטעמיך, u'letameich, הא דתניא, ha de-tanya,
according to you as it's taught, בעל ונישאת לעצמה, ba'al ve'nis'eis la'atzmah,
that if she had sex and then she was נשואה nesuah after
the rape and between the payment, then she does keep the money.
So where do you get that from? מי כתיב ונתן לאבי הנערה
אשר לא נשואה? mi ksiv venasan la'avi hana'arah asher lo nesuah? It
doesn't say pay the girl father—the father of the girl who is
not נשואה. nesuah. So why do we assume that when she's נשואה
nesuah at the time of the court case the money goes to
her? So he says back, הכי השתא? hachi hashta? What type of
comparison is that? התם, Hasam, when she gets נשואה nesuah between the
rape and the court case, we can say the following: הואיל ובגרות
מוציא מרשות אב. ho'il u'bagrus motzi mi-reshus av. The same way we
know that when she becomes a בוגרת bogeres between the rape and
the court case that she collects the money, because a normal בוגרת
bogeres is completely emancipated from the father. ונישואין מוציא מרשות אב, venisuin
motzi mi-reshus av, and we know that נישואין, nisuin, not אירוסין, eirusin,
but נישואין, nisuin, full marriage, emancipates her from the father in all
other areas of הלכה. halakhah. So since this is true in general
in הלכה halakhah that both בגרות bagrus and נישואין, nisuin, either one,
emancipates her from the father, that's a general rule. And therefore we
can say מה בגרות בעל ובגרה לעצמה? ma bagrus ba'al ve-bagrah la'atzmah?
The same way we have as a rule, we know this, I
mean רש"י Rashi quotes a פסוק pasuk how we know it from,
but the גמרא Gemara is taking it for granted, that we know
that after the act of rape if she became a בוגרת bogeres
before the court case, that in that case now that she's emancipated
at the time of the court case she keeps the קנס. knas.
אף נישואין, af nisuin, similar to נישואין nisuin which similarly fully emancipates
her from her father, בעל ונישאת לעצמה, ba'al ve-nis'eis la'atzmah, if there
was the rape and then she had נישואין, nisuin, לעצמה la'atzmah she
keeps the קנס. knas. So basically you don't need a פסוק pasuk
there. There it's almost self-evident if she's fully emancipated at the time
of the court case. So she keeps the money. We know it
by בגרות, bagrus, and we're going to say the same thing by
נישואין. nisuin. Okay. So, therefore, that makes sense. We don't need a
פסוק posuk for that.
So therefore,
okay, where were we?
אלא אירוסין, ella eirusin, by the way, Rashi just says that the
פסוק, posuk, one פסוק posuk we do know that says that she
keeps the money when she's a בוגרת bogeret is because it does
say ונתן לאבי הנערה. venasan la'avi hana'arah. That there, when it is
talking about the payment of the money, he's still described as אבי
הנערה avi hana'arah and we'll say אבי הנערה avi hana'arah not אבי
הבוגרת. avi habogeret. Okay. So בגרות bagrus and נישואין nisuin both emancipate
her. It says the money is paid לאבי הנערה. la'avi hana'arah. If
she's a בוגרת bogeret she keeps the money and therefore if she's
a נישואין nisuin she keeps the money. That makes sense. She's fully
emancipated and we know it by בוגרת, bogeret, we know it by
נישואין. nisuin. But here, אלא אירוסין, ella eirusin, but the normal case
of betrothal, that's like a, that normally doesn't emancipate her. מי קא
מפקי מרשות אב לגמרי, mi ka mafki mereshus av legamrei, she's not
fully out of the father's control. התנן, hasnan, נערה המאורסה, na'arah hame'orasah,
a woman who is betrothed, אביה ובעלה מפירין לה נדריה, aviha uva'alah
mefirin lah nedareha, both her father and her husband could sort of
annul the vows. She's under like both of their control. She's not
emancipated from anyone. She's actually under, she's both under the betrothed and
the, you know, the man and the father's control. So therefore, it's
a גזירת הכתוב gezeiras hakasuv according to Rabbi Akiva that if she's
raped after having been betrothed and freed, that the money goes to
her, but she's not in other ways emancipated in other דיני ממונות
dinei mammonos way. So therefore, if she becomes betrothed after the rape,
there's no logic why she should get the money. What? So, that's,
presumably she wouldn't get the money. There's no good logic to argue
yes, no logic, no פסוק, posuk, no ברייתא. braisa. Yeah. So my
question is this. I mean, the other part of this is, you
know, this is whether it's a rape or פיתוי, pittuy, you know,
that this should apply. I mean we, generally on, okay. So the
other part of the, aside from the קנס knas is also לו
תהיה לאשה, lo sihiyeh l'ishah, yeah, right? We're getting to that in
the next פסוק. posuk. Yeah. I know, but my question was like,
you know, would you also say that that falls away if she,
you know, gets out of בגרות, bagrus, that he doesn't have to
stay with her anymore, it's only, no no no no. This is
all just about payment and it's because of the relationship of her
to the father and who the money goes to. But he would
still be enforced as the, yeah, no, if he raped her after,
no no. The whole פרשה parsha only applies if she was a
נערה. na'arah. If he raped her as a בוגרת, bogeret, no, if
he raped her as a נערה na'arah and then she becomes a
בוגרת, bogeret, goes to the court, he still has to deal with
her.
Of course, of course. The only issue is the money issue. Maybe
that should, yes, he has to marry, he has to marry, is
that your question? He doesn't have to marry her. None of these
הלכות halachos apply. I mean you still have to apply because it's
an act of assault, you have to pay whatever payment you'd pay
at assault, whatever, whatever age she is or whatever. But in terms
of the special קנס knas and the special obligation to marry her,
that is only under the conditions when, of the Torah when she's
a נערה. na'arah. But the issue that if she becomes a בוגרת
bogeret later, that's only about money. That's only about whether the money
goes to her or to the father. The obligation to marry, yeah
yeah, the obligation to marry is not at all affected by that.
Okay. But it is affected by what her status was at the
time of the rape. Yes. Just to muddy the water, since her
father gets this קנס knas because presumably she's being devalued as a
prospective bride. Right. But if she becomes engaged, the קנס knas should
go to the חתן. chosson.
Well, we're going to see something similar to that later, but okay,
let's keep that in mind for the next discussion. So now we
finally, as is classic by the משניות, mishnayos, sort of the basic
information comes way at the end. Okay. So המפתה נותן שלושה דברים,
hamfayeh nosein sheloshah devarim,
right?
The seducer gives, pays, makes three payments. והאונס ארבע, veha'ones arba, and
the rapist four. So what are these? המפתה נותן בושת ופגם וקנס.
hamfayeh nosein boshes upgam uknas.
The seducer gives her בושת, boshes, the shame, money, money for the
shame. It's an act of assault, so they're normal payments with assault.
The normal payments with assault are שבת, sheves, loss of wages, ריפוי,
ripuy, medical bills. It's assumed that there is not going to be
the case, that, okay, that's the Gemara's assumption that even in the
case of rape, it's assuming there's not associated violence with the actual
violence, of violence of the rape itself. So assuming there's no ריפוי
ripuy and שבת, sheves, no medical bills or loss of wages while
the person was recuperating, that's the Gemara's assumption. But there is the
other three payments are נזק, nezek, the actual cost of the damage
itself, which is based on the whole slave market model,
בושת, boshes, the shame and embarrassment, and צער, tza'ar, the suffering, the
pain and suffering. Okay? So those are payments that are still going
to be present besides the קנס knas of the Torah. Now the
interesting thing is, is that in the case of מפתה, mifateh, of
seduction, why is there any payment? Like, you know, the woman agreed,
right? Why is it considered at all an act of assault? And
maybe it's because the woman agreed but the father didn't and how
much is she under the control of the father? So we're going
to have to ask that question why there's any payment in the
case of the seduction. You mentioned נזק nezek over here? No, that's
going to be the word פגם. pgam. One minute. המפתה נותן שלושה
דברים, hamfayeh nosein sheloshah devarim, האונס ארבע. ha'ones arba. המפתה נותן בושת,
hamfayeh nosein boshes, the payment for shame and embarrassment that comes through
an act. Of damage, of assault, of נזק, nezak, פגם, pgam, I'm
sorry, yeah, בושת ופגם וקנס. boshet u'pgam v'knas. המפתה נותן שלשה דברים,
האונס ארבעה. hamifateh nosein shlosha devarim, ha'oneis arba'ah. המפתה נותן בושת, hamifateh
nosein boshet, the payment for shame and embarrassment that comes through an
act of damage, of assault, of נזק, nezak, פגם, pgam, I'm sorry,
yeah, בושת ופגם וקנס. boshet u'pgam v'knas. פגם pgam is the פגם
pgam is the word that the משנה mishnah uses in the case
of אונס oneis and מפתה mifateh for נזק, nezak, for the damage
that is done. Now probably it uses the word פגם pgam as
opposed to נזק nezak because נזק nezak is like, you know, a
sort of observable physical, like it's a more of an externally visible
damage or like it's the classic damage whereas פגם pgam when you
think about a woman losing her virginity, it's more of like a
פגם pgam also has a certain moral taint to it, right. She's,
you know, somehow she's been, right, somehow she's been, I don't know,
besullied, thank you, right, stigma, not stigmatized, that's a little too hard.
Anyway, but it is the word that's being used in this context
for נזק, nezak, the payment for damages. Okay, there is no צער,
tza'ar, interesting, because if it's seduction, then presumably there was no pain
in it, right, it wasn't rape, so there's no צער. tza'ar. There
is בושת, boshet, which is interesting again because she did it willingly,
but also so there's בושת, boshet, there's פגם. pgam. So why there's
בושת boshet and פגם, pgam, why there's no צער, tza'ar, the assumption
is that there's just not the reality of pain. And the גמרא
gemara is going to question that. Okay, so there's no reality of
hospital bills, of lost wages, and of צער. tza'ar. There is the
גמרא gemara assumes a reality of פגם, pgam, why you of בושת,
boshet, why you pay that since she agreed is not clear. Okay,
and there is the פגם, pgam, the reality that now she's not
a virgin and that's a loss of her market value. Again, why
you pay it because she agreed isn't clear, but at least there's
that reality of בושת boshet and פגם. pgam. And קנס knas is
what the תורה torah says, that even in a case of seduction
you pay the fifty שקל, shekel, okay, because now she won't be
able to fetch the same price in the market. Okay, so again,
all of these things you could say why pay it she agreed,
but ultimately the answer is because she's only a קטנה ktanah or
she's only a נערה narah and therefore, you know, the father still
loses out and the payment still has to go to her, whether
she agreed to it or didn't agree to it. Okay, so those
are those three. One minute, מוסיף עליו האונס, mosif alav ha'oneis, the
אונס oneis adds on it, has those three, but he adds on
it שנותן את הצער, shenosein es hatza'ar, that there's also the pain
and suffering because it was an act of rape. Okay, again an
assumption, no hospital bills, no lost wages, but you do have the
embarrassment, pain and suffering, and the lost value, the נזק, nezak, plus
the קנס knas that the תורה torah says. You just helped me,
could you remind us in today's terms how much money are we
talking about חמשים שקל? chamishim shekel? Well, חמשים שקל chamishim shekel is
200 זוז. zuz. In the time, I don't know how much that
would be worth in that metal in today's market. More significantly, in
the time of the תורה, torah, in the time of the משנה,
mishnah, it was about it was about the like the amount of
money that was required to live off of for a year. Okay,
like at, like you know, at low wages, so I mean, like
at a low standard of living. So I don't know what that'd
be, $10,000 or something in today's terms? We're talking about $20,000 maybe.
Maybe, because people pay these things. I know, I know, but he's
talking about the fifty כסף, kessef, okay, yes. Yes, the value of
precious metals plummeted in the 16th century. Right, which is why there
were some changes to the כתובה ketubah and we started doing this
whole, even earlier started doing this whole thing about 200 זקוקים zequqim
because 200 זוז zuz was very little. Anyway, but forgetting the cost
of the metal, the buying power of it in the time of
the משנה mishnah was about the money to live off of for
a year. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says, okay, so moving
on, מה בין אונס למפתה? mah bein oneis l'mifateh? It's going to
repeat the same thing in different words, a little funny. What's the
difference? האונס נותן את הצער והמפתה אינו נותן את הצער. ha'oneis nosein
es hatza'ar v'hamifateh eino nosein es hatza'ar. Okay, thank you for pointing
that out. האונס נותן מיד, ha'oneis nosein miyad, now here's another difference
in addition to payment for pain and suffering. The אונס oneis pays
the קנס knas immediately, והמפתה לכשיוציא, v'hamifateh l'ksheiyotzi, the מפתה mifateh only
pays the קנס knas when he divorces her. Now what do you
mean divorces her? Actually the תורה torah says it means the גמרא's
gemara going to say it means when he chooses not to marry
her, right, because the תורה torah says by the by the מפתה,
mifateh, right, the תורה torah says by the מפתה, mifateh, if you
remember your פסוקים, psukim, it says מהור ימהרנה לו לאשה, mahor yimahrena
lo l'ishah, he should he should marry her for a wife, ואם
מאן ימאן אביה, v'im ma'ein yima'ein aviha, if the father refuses,
then כסף ישקל כמהר הבתולות. kessef yishkol k'mohar habetulos. So the מפתה
mifateh pays only if he doesn't marry her. The אונס oneis pays,
marries her, and pays immediately the קנס. knas. We'll discuss all why
all this is when we get to the גמרא. gemara. המפתה, hamifateh,
okay, האונס שותה בעציצו. ha'oneis shoseh b'atzitzo. The אונס oneis has to
drink with his own like pottery shard, which basically means, you know,
he raped this woman, he's got to marry her, whether he wants
to marry her or not. והמפתה אם רצה להוציא מוציא, v'hamifateh im
ratzah l'hotzi motzi, and the מפתה, mifateh, if he wants to divorce
her or he wants to not marry her, he's not only can
the father choose not to not to agree to it, he can
choose not to agree to it. כיצד שותה בעציצו? keitzad shoseh b'atzitzo?
What does it mean that he has to drink from his own
sort of like pottery shard?
Pot. Now this is unfortunately, it's so funny because the ישיבה yeshiva
was about to do a week on people with disabilities and again,
this is, whatever. I'll read this. Yeah, I will read this. It's
a very אפילו היא חגרת afilu hi chigeret even if she's lame,
אפילו היא סומא afilu hi suma even if she's blind, ואפילו היא
מוכת שחין vafilu hi mukat shechin or even if she has boils
all over her body. It doesn't matter. He raped her, he has
to marry her. Okay, obviously it's a very difficult גמרא Gemara in
terms of just ways of at least reflecting how people feel, people's
attitudes, even if it's not the גמרא's Gemara attitude, the משנה's Mishnah
attitude itself. נמצא בדבר ערוה, Nimtza bedvar ervah, now let's say it
turns out that this woman that he married now has committed adultery
after he married her. או שאינה ראויה לבוא בישראל, O she'einah re'uyah
lavo beYisrael, or other reasons that she's not allowed to marry a
Jew like she's a ממזרת. mamzeret. אינו רשאי לקיימה. Eino rashai lekayyemah.
In those circumstances he can't stay married to her or can't marry
her to begin with in the case of ממזרת. mamzeret. And there
the מצוה mitzvah to marry her does not override, שנאמר ולו תהיה
לאשה, shene'emar velo tihyeh le'ishah, he should be for her as a
wife, אשה ראויה לו, ishah re'uyah lo, only a wife who is
legally permitted to him. So if actually, even though he's forced to
marry her and he's not entitled to divorce her no matter what
other circumstances might be the case, if legally, הלכתית, halakhically, he's not
allowed to marry her or stay married to her then he does
not and then he divorces. I mean he doesn't marry her or
he divorces her. That's בעולת עצמו, be'ulat atzmo, yes. Kind of double
standards here. I mean, he violated her. Right. So it's almost poetic
justice if she goes out and has an affair with somebody.
Yeah, right. So here it's so funny. Exactly. Yeah, that's true. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to get, as I
said, to me the big question that jumps out of this משנה,
Mishnah, there's two big questions. One is why is there any payment
by מפתה mephateh if she agreed to it? And the other big
question is
what's the difference between that the אונס ones pays, the מפתה mephateh
pays only if he doesn't marry her and the אונס ones pays
even when he does marry, immediately and he marries her. So we'll
get to all of that, but the first issue that the גמרא
Gemara points out is neither of those two. The first issue the
גמרא Gemara points out is why is there not צער tza'ar in
the case assuming that you are going to pay by מפתה? mephateh?
So right, even though she agreed, so it's saying okay there's a
reality of embarrassment even though she agreed, certainly the father's embarrassed whether
she's embarrassed. There's a reality of פגם, pegam, of she's less valued
now because she's not a virgin. But why isn't there a reality
of צער? tza'ar?
Won't that be painful? Certainly it's the first time and so on.
Now you'd say okay, there might be some pain of the first
time of having intercourse, but if you do it willingly it's not
the same as the pain of an act of rape. Okay, but
let's take a look. That's what the גמרא Gemara wants to know,
why is there no צער tza'ar in the case of the מפותה?
mephutah? צער דמאי. Tza'ar demai. So first it says like this, what
is the צער tza'ar that's being paid by the case of the
rapist? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel: צער
tza'ar שחבטה על גבי קרקע. shechivtah al gabei karka. If he raped
her with a violent act, he threw her on the ground. So
again what is very funny here, look, it's
a very interesting גמרא Gemara we're going to talk about because it's
also about men, this is all through the lens of men. But
the sad thing about this גמרא Gemara is, I'll just tell you
ahead of time, that it does not recognize that the actual act
of intercourse, meaning not any attendant violence, but the actual act of
intercourse itself when a man is forcing himself upon a woman is
much more painful besides traumatic. I'm even bracketing the trauma aspect. I'm
just focusing on the physical experience, right? That if a woman isn't
ready, that act is obviously much more physically painful than it is
when a woman is willing and therefore ready for the act of
intercourse. The גמרא Gemara completely ignores that. And therefore only looks, when
it asks what's the additional צער tza'ar by rape, only looks at
attendant issues and not the actual act of intercourse itself. So let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this. וכי תימא: Vechi
teima: שחבטה
על גבי קרקע. shechivtah al gabei karka. Threw her to the ground.
מתקיף לה רב זירא: Matkif lah Rav Zeira: אלא מעתה חבטה על
גבי שיראין? ella me'atah chivtah al gabei shira'in? If he threw her
onto some pillows, some felt garments? Right. הכא נמי דפטור? hacha nami
depatur? Would you say there's no payment of צער? tza'ar? וכי תימא
הכא נמי: Vechi teima hacha nami: if you say yeah maybe that's
the case. והתניא רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון: Vehatanya
Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon: אונס אינו משלם את
הצער מפני שסופה להצטער תחת בעלה. Ones eino meshalem et hatza'ar mipnei
shesofah lehitztayeir tachat ba'alah.
So there's an opinion of the תנאים Tannaim that there is no
צער tza'ar by the case of rapist because anyway she's going to
have the pain of intercourse the first time she'll have intercourse with
her husband. So therefore the rapist shouldn't have to pay a payment
for suffering and pain that this woman will experience eventually in some
time of her life. Okay, which again just sort of sees no
difference in terms of the experience of intercourse whether it's consensual or
whether it is rape.
She's eventually going to suffer it, you don't pay for it now
just because it suffered early. But clearly we're talking about the pain
of intercourse and not seeing a difference between those two experiences. Yes.
Steinsaltz actually brings up the point that you just made. About what?
About forced intercourse. Well, of course. How could you not? But the
גמרא Gemara didn't. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמרו
לו אין דומה נבעלה באונס לנבעלה ברצון. Amru lo, ein domeh niva'alah
be-ones li-niva'alah be-ratzon. Now,
you don't need Steinsaltz, because that seems to be the response of
the גמרא. Gemara. But the funny thing is of the whatever in
the ברייתא, baraita, you know, which is even if you don't pay
now for something somebody is going to experience later anyway, now it's
not the same experience. Here it's rape. Now again, so that seems
to be exactly what we're saying, right? That seems to be exactly
like forced intercourse is obviously much more physically painful than consensual intercourse.
Okay, but the גמרא Gemara still does not get it. Okay, even
though that's almost exactly what this ברייתא baraita just said, or what
they exactly responded to him, the גמרא Gemara still wants to say,
but where is the extra pain? So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה,
ela amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, צער שפיסוק הרגלים. tza'ar
she-pissuk haraglayim.
When he forced her legs open, that's the צער. tza'ar. וכן הוא
אומר ותפסקי את רגליך לכל עובר, ve-khen hu omer, va-tifteki et raglayikh
le-khol over, you opened up your legs to anyone who would pass
by. אי
הכי, ei hakhi, says the גמרא, Gemara, מפותה נמי. mefuttah nami. Does
she actually mean sexually mean like, you know, no, they actually mean
sex, they actually mean the physical act of forcing her legs open
in the act of rape. She's trying to protect herself. Right, and
he's forcing her to open. So again, it's so funny that it
is not talking about the actual act of intercourse itself being forced
intercourse is itself, you know, terribly painful. No, it's talking about the
attendant issues. So the גמרא Gemara says, if that's true, מפותה נמי,
mefuttah nami,
so in a case of seduction as well, he opens up her
legs. Again, isn't there a difference between whether she's trying to keep
her legs closed and being forced open as opposed to not? Very
strange גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה משל דמפותה
למה דבר דומה, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, mashal de-mefuttah
le-ma dabar domeh,
so the גמרא Gemara now says, no, here's why it's different. Because
in a case of seduction, what it's like of a woman being
seduced? לאדם שאומר לחבירו קרע שיראים שלי והפטר, le-adam she-omer le-chavero kra
shirayim sheli u-patter, tear my nice silk garment and you'll be exempt,
which means yes, there is physical pain by the opening of the
legs in the case of the מפותה, mefuttah, but she's okay with
it. She says, I want you to do it, and therefore you
don't have to pay. So again, what's strange is, the גמרא Gemara
says, you know what the difference is between seduction and rape? Is
she's okay with it. But it doesn't say that the difference is
that in one case it's much more physically painful than the other.
Even before you get to the act of intercourse itself, just the
forcing open of somebody else's legs as opposed to somebody willingly opening
their legs, right? You would say one case it's painful, the other
case it's not painful. The גמרא Gemara seems as though no, the
actual pain is the exact same. The only difference is in one
case since she agreed to it, you don't have to pay because
she said you can go ahead and do it, I'm okay with
it. So therefore you don't have to pay. But the actual pain
is the exact same. So the גמרא Gemara says, שלי, sheli, you
can go ahead, tear my garment as it were, דאבוה נינהו? d'avu'ah
nihu? It's her father's. Her pain or whatever is her father's. This
gets back to why even in a case of פיתוי, pittuy, of
seduction, there is payment for both בושת boshet and פגם, pgam, because
she's not entitled to give that away, as it were. The father
still has rights and control. She's not entitled to give it away,
so even in the case of פיתוי, pittuy, there are going to
be these payments. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say, so
if there were צער tza'ar as well, if there was pain as
well in the case of פיתוי, pittuy, even if she was okay
with it and she said I want it, nevertheless she's not entitled
to give it away, and the father, a נערה na'arah or קטנה,
ktanah, the father therefore should still collect. Okay, so number one, we've
in two words indicated why in the משנה Mishnah there's all these
payments even though she agreed, because she's not entitled to agree. The
father has rights, the father has control, even if she's okay, the
father still says no and he's entitled to collect. But what the
גמרא Gemara still is resisting or not able to understand is that
there is a physically painful different experience in the case of rape
and in the case of seduction. Whether it's in terms of what
it's calling now forcing the woman's legs open or whether it's in
the actual just act of intercourse itself, there's a dramatic physical difference
in terms of the actual pain experienced in those two cases. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes.
אלא אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה פקחות שבין אומרות מפותה
אין לה צער. ela amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, pikchos
she-bein omros mefuttah ein lah tza'ar. Now, you know, the wise women
say, or I don't know, פקחות pikchos here means anyway, what's relevant
here is that a woman who is seduced doesn't have pain. So
the גמרא Gemara says, והא קא חזינן דאית לה, ve-ha ka chazinan
de-it lah, but we know women have pain whenever it's the first
time, even if they do it willingly. Again. And you know, the
pain of the initial act of sex, even if it is willing.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אמרי לי אם,
Amri li eim, my mother, which doesn't mean his mother, means his
nursemaid; his mother died when he was young, said to me, describe
to me what that experience was like, the pain of having sex
for the first time, consensual sex. כמיא חמימי על רישא דקרחא, K'maya
chamimei al reisha d'karcha,
like pouring hot water on a bald head. Presumably the point being
made is that it's a little bit painful but it's also pleasurable
as well. Okay, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אמרי לי בת רב חסדא.
Amri li bas Rav Chisda. So the daughter of רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda,
which is רבא's Rava wife, said to me, my wife said to
me, כריבדא דכוסילתא, Ki rivda d'kuslisa, like the puncture made by, you
know, the horn of the bloodletter, okay, so maybe again it's a
little bit painful but maybe also some pleasure comes as a result.
רב פפא אמר, Rav Papa amar, אמרי לי בת אבא סורא, Amri
li bas Abba Sura, the daughter of אבא סורא, Abba Sura, which
is his wife, said to me, כנהמא דכושכשי בחינכי, Ki nama d'kushk'shei
b'chinkhei,
like hard bread against your cheek, so when you're chewing it. So
again there's pleasure even though there's some pain accompanying it. So basically
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, is that yes there is
pain for a מפותה, mefuta, a little pain in the first time
a woman has sex, but there's no payment of צער tzaar because
ultimately the pleasure outweighs the pain, it's ultimately a pleasurable act in
the case of consensual sex for the first time. But non-consensual sex,
there is pain. But at the end of the day, do we
know what the pain is? It sounds like the pain is just,
you know, the act because it's the first time and the rupturing
of the hymen, right, which isn't outweighed by the pleasure, like the
גמרא Gemara never directly acknowledged that the real pain we're talking about
here is the forced act
itself. Forced. Not the attendant issues, you know, but whatever, and there
as well, like the legs and opening the legs or whatever could
also be the painful, but the forced act itself, that that's the
real point, right, the גמרא Gemara never really gets to that. It
seems like that was in the line where it says אינה דומה
נבעלת באונס לנבעלת ברצון, Eina doma nivalis b'ones linvalis b'ratzon, but the
גמרא Gemara kept on sort of going around that issue. So that
was a, it's a very challenging גמרא. Gemara. And then we actually
says that, like you know, who do you have to pay for
it, we ask a small girl, like how much would you be
willing to pay? Well, that's always the question about how do you
assess pain and suffering. How much would somebody be willing to accept
to endure this type of a thing? Or how much would you
be willing to pay to not have to endure? I should by
the way mention there's another interesting question here which I sort of
bracketed is how much does the payment of צער tzaar also include
trauma and psychological צער? tzaar? You think about it. It's one thing
to say physical pain, but look, even in the case of extreme
pain, right, that's why we say pain and suffering. Like if somebody
endured extreme pain, much more long-lasting is the traumatic aspect than the
actual physical sensation of the time. And so if you want to
focus on that, there's also a huge difference between rape and seduction.
There's a world of difference. So again, the fact that the גמרא
Gemara sort of brackets can't understand those differences is challenging and disturbing.
Okay, we will end with this here. The psychological aspects of the.